Hello, Friends, I'm Munendra and you are...
Welcome back to a new video of my Youtube channel.
Today, In this video, we will talk about NCB or
No claim Bonus. What is NCB?
When and how we get NCB discount?
When we can take the benefit of NCB?
If the policy of your vehicle is Expired.
Then, will you get the benefit of NCB?
If you have sold out your vehicle, what will happen to NCB?
Will  NCB discount will be transferred to you or..
the NCB will be transferred to the person who purchased the vehicle.
While the renewal of the policy we have the option to choose NCB,
So, if we select more NCB, then what will happen?
The policy will be cancelled or we will have to face any problem?
So, this video will answer these all your questions.
You should watch the video till END
So, you will understand better.
Now, let's start the video....
The very first question; What is NCB?
The NCB is called NO Claim Bonus.
Which is an award or discount provided to the Insured person
by the company.
If the owner of the vehicle has not made any claim,
during the policy period or Twelve months.
A discount is offered at the time of renewal of the policy.
Because you have not made any claim...
and You have benefited the company. So, the company offers a discount.
When and how much NCB discount is offered?
NCB is a discount is provided as per this table.
If you have not made any claim during the preceding ...full year of insurance.
So at the time of policy renewal for the next year, you will get 20% NCB Discount.
If you don't claim in the one more next year,
then at the time of second-time policy renewal
you will get a 25% NCB Discount.
Likewise, if you don't claim for the preceding five years
at the time of policy renewal for the sixth year,
you will get a 50% NCB discount.
The NCB discount can be a maximum of 50%
it will not go more than 50%, but...
meanwhile, if you made any claim.
Suppose, in the sixth year, you made with an accident and you claim.
Then you NCB will be cancelled or become zero.
Now, you have to earn it again by making no claim.
If you don't claim in the seventh year, you will earn 20% NCB.
Now, is this NCB discount is applicable on the total premium?
The 20%,  35% or 50% NCB,
Does it mean you will have to pay only
50% of the net premium of the policy?
the answer is, NO. as the NCB is computed only on OD premium.
or the Own Damage premium component.
We can understand it like;
there are a lot of coverages in our policy
the net premium is calculated by adding all components of the premium of different covers.
So the premium component which
covers only your vehicle,
or it is called Basic OD [Own Damage] Premium
The NCB Discount percentage,
is to be computed on this Basic OD Premium factor.
For better understanding let's take an example of a policy.
This is an ICIC Lombard Zero Dep. car policy.
As you can see the total premium is INR Rs. 31,910/
But the policy has two sections.
The one is A section or the Own Damage section
Which is related to your own vehicle covers
Our vehicle, or any other our mishaps.
The second section is the B section or third party section
or the Liability section.
So, in the OD section, there is Zero Dep. cover
and 5670 Rs. for Zero dep. cover
1638 Rs. is for the cover for consumables
and Rs. 14743 is for the Basic OD premium.
So the 20% NCB in the policy,
will be calculated on Basic OD premium
and that is Rs. 14743.
So, 20% of Rs. 14743 is Rs. 2948.6
So the discount here is Rs. 2949
is provided as the no claim bonus.
and not getting 20% of the total premium.
likewise, if NCB would be 50% then we would be getting is 50% of the Basic OD premium not of the total.
Here OD Premium is Rs. 14743 so,
we would be getting around Rs. 7371.5
When can we get the benefit of NCB?
The benefit of NCB is availed at the time of the renewal of the policy.
after twelve months of the policy without making any claim.
But if...
You forgot to take the benefit at the time of renewal of the policy,
You can take at later on as well.
Company will return you the access amount paid by you,
or the NCB discount amount.
Now, if the policy is expired.
will you get NCB discount or not?
So, if your policy is expired in the last 45 days.
and you are renewing the policy within 45 days.
then you will get the NCB Benefit.
But...
If your policy is expired more than 45 days ago.
No claim bonus will be cancelled and you can not get it.
Q. If you have sold out your vehicle, how the NCB is transferred?
Will the NCB transferred to you or the buyer?
we can understand it simply by the fact that.
the NCB is entitled to the Insured person,
Not the vehicle or the policy.
So, when you sell your vehicle, the NCB will be with you.
Whenever you buy a new vehicle.
You can get the benefit of the NCB in the policy of that new vehicle.
It should be availed withing THREE Years.
You can buy a new vehicle within the next THREE years
and get your NCB benefit transferred to that policy
Q. If we select more NCB at the time of renewal of the policy?
Suppose you are eligible to get 35% NCB discount,
and you select it 45% or 50%
Then the company will issue an NCB Recovery letter and send it to you.
and whatever the more NCB benefit you have availed,
You will have to pay it to the company.
Otherwise, your policy may be canceled.
Before this notice, you make any claim
or you made with any accident then,
Then you claim will not be processed until
You pay that amount.
So in this video, I covered all the possible questions related to NCB.
and I tried to answer them.
If you still have any questions, you may ask in comment section.
or message me on Instagram
the username is Indian.Munendra
I hope you liked this video and ...
you got the answer to your questions related to NCB.
If you find this video helpful, please hit LIKE.
If you want to watch more of my videos,
Then Please hit the Subscribe button and press the bell icon.
It's totally FREE...